Suchismit Mahapatra

RESEARCH SCIENTIST · (MACHINE LEARNING | DEEP LEARNING

Criteo Al Lab, 325 Lytton Avenue, Palo Alto, CA 94301

□ (+1) 716-435-8865 | Suchismi@buffalo.edu | Ahttps://schrilax.github.io/ | Suchismit | S

About Me

I am currently a Research Scientist with Criteo. Broadly, my work encompasses applying different Machine Learning, Deep Learning and Nonlinear Optimization techniques to solve related problems. I completed my PhD with the Machine Learning and Data Science Research (MLDS) group at The State University of New York at Buffalo (UB), working under Varun Chandola.

Research Interests

Broadly, my area of research is in large scale machine learning and data mining. Specifically my research focuses on designing, analyzing and implementing novel machine learning algorithms that take advantage of modern hardware to enable learning and mining of massive graphs and data sets. My research interests include:

- Machine Learning
- · Deep Learning
- Nonlinear/Distributed Optimization

- · Data Mining
- · Parallel Computing
- Social Networks

Academic Background _

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

September 2012 - June 2018

- Topic: Scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods for streaming data.
- Advisors: Varun Chandola, Nils Napp & Jaroslaw Zola
- GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 (Transcript 🔼)

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY September 2010 - August 2012

Buffalo, NY

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

• Topic: A Cold Start Recommendation System Using Item Correlation and User Similarity.

- GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 (Transcript 区)
- Department rank: 1 out of 555

National Institute of Technology, Rourkela

Rourkela, India

B.Tech. IN Computer Science and Engineering

• Cumulative Score: 77% (First class with honors)(Transcript 🖾)

• Joint Entrance Exam Rank 22 out of 400,000

August 2001 - May 2005

Honors _

2019	Was invited to and attended the prestigious Foundations of Deep Learning program.	Berkeley, CA
2017	Won a NSF Junior Researcher Award to attend CBMS Conference on Sparse Recovery.	Las Cruces, NM
2016	Became a NVIDIA GPU Educator.	Santa Clara, CA
2015	Won a NSF Student Travel Award to attend IEEE Big Data 2015.	Santa Clara, CA
2013	Won a rare Research Assistant-ship covering my second year as a Masters student.	Buffalo, NY
2008	Won the Star Performer of the Month award in Cognizant.	Kolkata, India
2007	Won the Outstanding Newbie award in Cognizant.	Kolkata, India
2004	Scored 99 percentile in Zonal, Discipline and National categories of National IT Aptitude Test.	Rourkela, India
2004	Subsequently won a Bhavishya Jyoti Scholarship for above.	Rourkela, India
1999	Won the Young Genius award.	Cuttack, India

Skills & Proficiencies _

Python, C/C++, TensorFlow, Scala, Hive, CUDA

Experience _____

Criteo Research Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST

July 2018 - Present

- Improve Click-through and Sales prediction
 - Understanding how to improve Click-through and Sales prediction using nonlinear ML techniques.
- Theoretical aspects on Deep Learning (DL) (working with Noureddine El Karoui)
 - Working towards understanding kernel and manifold specific aspects of theoretical deep learning.

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

January 2018 - May 2018

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Parallelized Hierarchical Clustering (working with Haimonti Dutta)
- Worked towards developing a novel parallel hierarchical clustering algorithm using activization strategies.
- Kernel Manifold Learning (working with Varun Chandola)
 - Worked towards developing Manifold Learning techniques motivated from Gaussian Processes. 🔼

Criteo Research

Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

September 2017 - December 2017

- Efficient Domain Adaptation (working with Suju Rajan)
 - Understanding how to efficiently deal with the Domain Adaptation problem via Optimal Transportation.

Criteo Research

Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

May 2017 - August 2017

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

- Cross-domain Query-Product (QP) modeling using Adversarial Transfer Learning (working with Suju Rajan)
- Trying to learn a robust QP model across retailer domains using Adversarial Transfer Learning. 🚨

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

January 2017 - May 2017

- Representation learning via DL/NLSDR methods (working with Varun Chandola / Nils Napp / Jaroslaw Zola)
 - Understanding complex nonlinear processes using DL/NLSDR methods. 🚨 🛗 🛗
- Incorporating complex constraints for sparse Logistic Regression (working with Varun Chandola)

 Worked towards solving the sparse Logistic Regression problem with hierarchical tree-based constraints.

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

TEACHING ASSISTANT

BD Biosciences

September 2016 - December 2016

Teaching Assistant for CSE 574 Machine Learning.

Machine Learning Algorithm Design Intern

San Jose, CA

- Fast Clustering of Flow Cytometry (FC) data
 - Scaling up BD's clustering framework for high dimensional FC data upto ~16x. 🔼 🔀

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

TEACHING ASSISTANT

January 2016 - May 2016

June 2013 - December 2015

June 2016 - August 2016

• Teaching Assistant for CSE 574 Machine Learning.

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction (working with Varun Chandola / Jaroslaw Zola / Nils Napp)
- Developed scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods in a streaming setting. 🚨
- Social Network Modeling (working with Varun Chandola)
 - Developed the xKPGM model for social network modeling. 🔼
- Variance Reduction techniques in Distributed Optimization (working with Haimonti Dutta / Varun Chandola)
 Working towards developing novel variance reduction techniques for the ERM problem.
- Understanding Rumor Propagation in Social Networks (working with Shambhu Upadhyaya / Varun Chandola)
 Working towards modelling rumor propagation in social networks.
- Volcanic Flow Prediction (working with Abani Patra / Varun Chandola / Paul Bauman)
 - Developed a Gaussian Process based model for prediction of flow using GPGPUs.

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

TEACHING ASSISTANT

September 2012 - May 2013

• Teaching Assistant for CSE 510 Introduction to Robotic Algorithms.

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

June 2011 - August 2012

- Localization via Entropy Reduction (working with Robert Platt)
 - Developed an active localization technique via sequential reduction of entropy using OpenRAVE/ROS. 🔼 🛗
- AIRS (working with Rakesh Nagi)
 - Developed sequential/parallel versions of TRUncated Search Tree algorithm.
- Name2Face (working with Bina Ramamurthy)
 - Developed Name2Face, a cloud application consuming Microsoft cloud services).

Cognizant

Kolkata, India

June 2005 - July 2010

- ASSOCIATE
- Developed ExProc, a tool for processing excel documents.
- Built SuperAgent 4.0, a tool for making reservations which interacts with the Novasol and Cuendet servers.
- · Developed Universal Agent Tool along with my team, a tool which aimed at merging operations for various CRS.
- Contributed to a white paper Using Venn Diagrams to capture Business Requirements.

Publications

- 1. Modeling Graphs Using a Mixture of Kronecker Models. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. Proceedings of the 3rd IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2015.
- 2. Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. **Suchismit Mahapatra**, Frank Schoeneman, Varun Chandola, Jaroslaw Zola, Nils Napp. Proceedings of SIAM Data Mining Conference, 2017
- 3. S-Isomap++: Multi Manifold Learning from Streaming Data. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. Proceedings of 5th IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2017
- 4. Learning Manifolds from Non-stationary Streaming Data. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. (In submission)
- 5. A Generalized Out-of-Sample Extension Framework for Streaming NLSDR. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. (Under preparation)

Seminar/Symposia _____

2017	S-Isomap++: Multi Manifold Learning from Streaming Data. (IEEE Big Data 2017) 🔼	Boston, NY
2017	Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. (SIAM SDM 2017) 🖹	Houston, TX
2016	Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. (UB Computer Science Mixer) 🔼	Buffalo, NY
2016	Fast Clustering of Flow Cytometry Data via Adaptive Mean Shift. (BD Biosciences) 🚨 🔼	San Jose, CA
2015	Modeling Graphs Using a Mixture of Kronecker Models. (IEEE Big Data 2015) 🔼	Santa Clara, CA
2012	Entropy-based localization framework for localizing known objects. (NEMS 2012) 描	Bedford, MA

Activities ____

- Part of organizing committee for KDCloud [2014], BigSpatial [2014, 2015, 2016, 2017].
- Student Member of IEEE, SIAM and ACM.

Additional Coursework/Projects _____

- Implemented 3PRR Parallel Chain and PRRR Serial Chain Manipulators under Venkat Krovi 內內
- Developed ElGooG A search engine using ~100000 TREC documents as corpus (won the NTipS 2010 competition) 🔀
- Machine Learning course offered by Stanford under Andrew Ng

References _____

- Professor Varun Chandola
 Department of Computer Science & Engineering
 University of Buffalo, The State University of New York
 chandola@buffalo.edu
- Professor Shambhu Upadhyaya
 Department of Computer Science & Engineering
 University of Buffalo, The State University of New York
 shambhu@buffalo.edu